Benjamin Houghton: Okay. So
Benjamin Houghton: we left off last time talking about kind of the overall configurations or the overall architecture and configurations of resnet.
Benjamin Houghton: We saw that you know the major.
Benjamin Houghton: Really, the the major difference between the Bgg architecture and resnet was this idea of skip connections which allowed for much deeper network, and and also.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, there's some small minor details like the last layer, for example, is this average pooling as opposed to like a flattening layer, that you might that you would see in like Vgg architecture.
Benjamin Houghton: So one other thing we should probably
Benjamin Houghton: take a quick look at is kind of the results of in this in the resnet paper, and
Benjamin Houghton: we can see here where ultimately they're essentially able to to train a deeper network at
Benjamin Houghton: here you have the
Benjamin Houghton: a plain 18 layer versus a red you have. The actually, what they're showing here in this plot is is pretty interesting. So we have the an 18 layer and a 34 layer, and we see that the validation error is actually higher on the 34 layer. But when we plot the validation error
Benjamin Houghton: with the
Benjamin Houghton: resnet. Now, so this is the resin architecture, 18 resnet versus a 34 resnet, and this was on Imagenet. We see that the 34 layer actually outperforms the 18 layer resnet as well as it. It also outperforms the the architectures without the residual connection. So
Benjamin Houghton: this kind of proves, in a sense that it's it's well the their whole paper proves it. But this is just their quantifiable evidence on an image net. But you know we already discussed this earlier that there's, you know, even much larger architectures like 5,100 152. And and you can essentially keep going deeper and deeper to an extent.
Benjamin Houghton: those of you, I guess the one caveat to that is what some of you may or may not have picked up on is
Benjamin Houghton: these, one by one, convolutions that they do in these residual connections. So what is kind of like the problem with that from a back propagation standpoint. Well, the whole idea, this, like earlier, we were saying that.
Benjamin Houghton: remember the the gradient can flow. If we have again.
Benjamin Houghton: we have Z equals F of x plus x, no matter what F of X is, no matter what the derivative of FA. Of X is, the gradient can flow through can flow completely through
Benjamin Houghton: through X, right? So essentially this allows
Benjamin Houghton: the upstream gradient of Z, so the would be the gradient of Z with respect to the loss or the gradient of the loss with respect to Z.
Benjamin Houghton: Times one. Here, because the gradient of of X is just one right, so the the gradient, the upstream gradient, can pass fully through this this term here, even if this term is 0 right? Because, remember, it would if we said, if we had the gradient. And this is a really bad place to write this, let me write it down here, actually in the margin. So if we remember, if we have the gradient.
Benjamin Houghton: say we have the gradient of the cost, we'll say the cost this time with a J. With respect to Z right, and this is if we have this term right. That means the gradient of X
Benjamin Houghton: with respect to J is going to be equal to
Benjamin Houghton: the gradient of what was going to be the gradient of F with respect to X plus just
Benjamin Houghton: one right? Because the derivative or the of X is just one. So no matter.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, I'm sorry times right? I forgot my chain rule right here. That's the whole point of this times. The gradient of X. With respect to the cost, right? So even if this term is a really small number like 0 point 0 1, or whatever it may be, you know it's not typical that this would be necessarily small number. But the idea here is that
Benjamin Houghton: If you did this, multiply these fractions over and over again. Then eventually you'd run into a scenario where the these fractions, keeping multiplied by themselves over and over again, would end up a really small gradient being propagated through the network, and that plus X term helps alleviate that. Because again, let me rewrite this a little bit cleaner. Now, the
Benjamin Houghton: for you guys, the gradient of
Benjamin Houghton: the gradient of the cost. With respect.
Benjamin Houghton: 2 x. Is equal to the gradient
Benjamin Houghton: of what did we say of the cost? With respect to Z times the gradient of
Benjamin Houghton: F with respect to Z, plus one
Benjamin Houghton: right? So no matter what we can see, the upstream gradient can flow back through the network. Always
Benjamin Houghton: okay? And and so what I was getting at. And I know we talked about that in the last video just wanted to refresh everyone's memory on that. But
Benjamin Houghton: what I was saying is with these, one by one convolutions is that it has a stride of 2 and so, in a sense.
Benjamin Houghton: if we're skipping every other pixel value like, while it's still a much better
Benjamin Houghton: while the gradient can still flow back through.
Benjamin Houghton: because, you know, every convolution, you know, when we do a convolution, let's draw this out real fast. Actually, we do a convolution right with a 3 by 3 convolution. So here's my image this big box right? And here's my kernel. And so this kernel has is is a function of of 3 of of actually, I'm sorry. 9 numbers 3 by 3. So
Benjamin Houghton: when we do a convolution we have these 9 digits, or these 9 values that are contributing to a single value in the image right like. And here's the output image. And you're gonna do this. You know, this kernel is going to slide across with a stride of one. And so every single.
Benjamin Houghton: every single
Benjamin Houghton: pixel is gonna contribute to what's that? Roughly 9. If assuming you're not on the edges, it's gonna contribute to 9 different calculations or 9 different convolution operations. Right? So, while every single pixel is still going to
Benjamin Houghton: even this pixels that get skipped and the one by one convolution, the gradient can still sort of flow back to them.
Benjamin Houghton: right, if you have a if we do a
Benjamin Houghton: here, I was saying with these dash lines where they do a 1 by one convolution with a
Benjamin Houghton: with one they do one by one convolution. So that means they skip every other pixel with stride it, too. Right? So if you have a an image, and let's we'll make a small one here. It's just say 4 by 4 image here right? And we do a 1 by one convolution. Well, we're gonna take our one by one by one
Benjamin Houghton: convolution with Xtrita, too. So this value is going to contribute this. Maybe I should use a different symbol. Right? So actually, let's do this. So this value is going to contribute this one's not. This value is going to contribute this one's not so when we have this stride of 2. Essentially, we're skipping every other pixel and so.
Benjamin Houghton: therefore the gradient does not. You know these values, these pixels? Essentially, they don't contribute to the downstream gradient any longer. And so when we were due to do a back propagation in this layer, and a 1 by one convolution strategy. They would not affect this operation right now. They would still pass.
Benjamin Houghton: They would still get
Benjamin Houghton: a gradient through the normal convolution operations. Because, like, so this is the input. Right this is X into some layer. Right? So this is XX gets go, and x goes. What what happens to X. Well, remember, Z, or actually, we'll use their notation. We'll, you know, we probably should be using their notation H of x right, which is equal to
Benjamin Houghton: what they say. F of x plus x, right. So the gradient still flows through this. But these pixels here, right.
Benjamin Houghton: these pixels that in the one by one convolution they don't contribute to this, because this isn't actually plus x, this is actually plus
Benjamin Houghton: a 1 by one convolution with a strita, too. Right? So the gradient can't flow as easily through this when we do the one by one convolution. So it kind of negates a lot of what the purpose of resnet is. So that's like the only caveat that you should really understand again, like it's still way better than no residual consections like, and you have to have a way, I guess, to kind of.
Benjamin Houghton: You know you have to have a way to down sample. Right? So and this is the way they chose to do it right. So you know, it would be interesting to know how much the one by one convolution, really affects things, as far as allowing the gradient to flow back, like, you know, preventing some of the gradient flow. I I don't really know but exactly how much it would quantify to, but just be aware of that. Okay,
Benjamin Houghton: So I think that pretty much wraps it up for for resnet. I think you know. What we'll do now is we'll go back to
Benjamin Houghton: the presentation, and we'll start talking about dense net now.
Benjamin Houghton: So what is dense net. So dense net is
Benjamin Houghton: the best way I can describe it, like I just said in the other video is, it's it's kind of almost you can kind of think of it like a densely connected feed forward network in the sense where every single input gets used in every single other output or every single, not output. Every single input.
Benjamin Houghton: every single output gets used for for all the other layers. Essentially right? So in a in a conventional.
Benjamin Houghton: when we have a conventional feed forward network, right? Like we have.
Benjamin Houghton: we have like an input layer. Let's let's draw this. We'll make some nice colors. Here. Let's say the red circles are the input layer. Okay? And the blue circles are the hidden layer, the whatever. It's a feet densely connected. Layer. And you know this gets used in in every single layer right like, and so does this one, this node and this drawing is getting messy quick. But
Benjamin Houghton: that's the idea, right, that each node contributes to every every input, node or every you know, or every input gets used in every hidden node. So this isn't exactly the way a dense net is, but you'll see here in a minute. It's kind of that inter. It has a lot of that interconnectivity. So
Benjamin Houghton: if you look at this diagram on the right here, we actually see that. So this is what we call this is what they call a a dense light a dense block, right? So this is would be, we see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Usually, I think they have 6 of these convolutions stacked like this I don't. I don't know. If there's a set number. We'll look at the configurations here in a minute. But
Benjamin Houghton: the output from this convolution gets used here.
Benjamin Houghton: here, here and here, right? And it's not just and well, you're like, well, yeah, well, how is that different than a convolution? Well, it's actually the output of this goes to the green layer. So that's the very next step, right? The green layer convolves, whatever the red layer was like, whatever came from the red layer, and then it adds right. The green and the red get added. They get concatenated together, and they both go into the purple right? So like what is like that's like kind of like saying.
Benjamin Houghton: if the that's like, it's like saying, X, 0 way they do, it is
Benjamin Houghton: how how would we write this? Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, X goes. Let's say, h, 1 is the red layer, right? And it's a function of X, okay? And then it produces. I'll say I don't know y. 1. And so then h, 2 is the green layer, and it's actually a function of X and
Benjamin Houghton: and y 1 right.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, and it produces y 2,
Benjamin Houghton: all right, and so on and so forth. So maybe you can see the pattern already. So then the purple layer we'll call it h, 3 is a function of X,
Benjamin Houghton: y. 1, and guess what y 2 right and so, and it produces y. 3. And so essentially.
Benjamin Houghton: what we're doing here is that we're
Benjamin Houghton: we're using all the outputs and and on like. And you might be saying, Well, how is this different from Resnet? Well in resnet, we did F of x
Benjamin Houghton: plus X, right? We're not. We're not saying that at all. Here. What we're saying actually is F of X,
Benjamin Houghton: actually, what we're doing is concatenating them together. So rather than adding matrices, we're stacking them. So now this would be concat
Benjamin Houghton: F of X and X, okay, we're out of room. Sorry. But yeah, I'm not crazy about this pen. It's kind of messy looking
Benjamin Houghton: in this software. I I might sorry about that guys. I might try to change that, because, like, it's kind of hard to write with this pen. But anyways.
Benjamin Houghton: let's see.
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. So we're concatenating the layers together. And and you're like, well, like how many you might, you might be thinking to yourself, well, that's that's like a lot of channels. And well, yeah, it is. And there's actually there's they do things to kind of control that in dense net. But
Benjamin Houghton: if the output, let's say y. 1 is is 4 channels.
Benjamin Houghton: Right? Well, let's say let's say there, let's say the output of let's say X is is 4 channels right?
Benjamin Houghton: See? XX is 4 channels.
Benjamin Houghton: And let's say, y, 1 is also 4 channels, and and y, 2 is also 4 channels. Well, then, let's see the input, to H, 3, right? So the out this way has 4 channel output. This is a 4 channel output, and X is 4 channels. So guess what how many channels get input into the purple layer. Well, it you're it's 12, right? It's 4 plus 4 plus 4 and so that's essentially how this works.
Benjamin Houghton: And the idea here is that you're kind of like reusing in a sense.
Benjamin Houghton: what? Maybe the earlier layers determined. Right? You're not just kind of throwing it away right? And so like. What do I mean by that? Well.
Benjamin Houghton: again, like in resnet, when we're adding like, yes, like the information can flow
Benjamin Houghton: more backward, like the the gradients, and and again, like the thing about resident, is really more about the gradients, more than the forward passive information. So yes, like some of that information does flow through like F of x right, but like
Benjamin Houghton: F of x plus x, right? But
Benjamin Houghton: you lose some of the meaning of what X was right like, and you also lose some of the meaning of what F of X was right. So this this kind of separates it, and it allows each layer to kind of determine for itself what to pay attention to right. It's kind of like in a in a dense feed forward network. It would be kind of weird if you think about it like this. If here's our input layer again, we'll go back to our dense network and
Benjamin Houghton: like each blue dot gets a copy of every single of every single red dot, right?
Benjamin Houghton: Every single red dot and gets a gets to look at every single you know. Every single
Benjamin Houghton: layer in the blue sees every layer in the red or every node, I should say not layer, and this allows the and and they have a parameter or a weight for each associated with one right? That's deep learning. 101. We already know this. And so essentially the blue dots the blue nodes can determine for themselves, hey? Which nodes are important to them
Benjamin Houghton: rather than like. What if we were to add all these together. That would be kind of weird right? And then so the blue dot wouldn't really know where the information came from per se, or it would only know what the the would only ever see the end product right? So it wouldn't be able to distinguish between them. And so that's the idea of this, of this dense network, and
Benjamin Houghton: again like it, it improves upon. Look image net, right like I said before, that's that's kind of the benchmark. At least one, you know Cfr 10 is is our Cfr. Is the benchmark as well. But
Benjamin Houghton: sorry. Yeah.
Benjamin Houghton: What I was saying was that
Benjamin Houghton: imagenet's the benchmark, and once again we see that it's what it's compared to, and the dense net should improve, you know, proves upon the performance of resnet.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright alright! Let's get a little bit more into this, and we'll take a look here on the next slide.
Benjamin Houghton: And the dense net architecture. Right? So again, we see that standard again, like we see that standard input 3
Benjamin Houghton: by 2, 2, 4 by 2, 2, 4 RGB images.
Benjamin Houghton: We have the dense blocks which we just talked about, and where each layer gets receives input from all the preceding layers.
Benjamin Houghton: And you know those inputs are concatenated together rather than added like that is a key difference here, right like you had like this is the. This is the difference between resident and dense net concatenation versus addition that is really
Benjamin Houghton: more or less the the main, I mean, that is pretty much the
Benjamin Houghton: the theme here. Or were the main differences so.
Benjamin Houghton: and they have a thing called growth rate, where you know.
Benjamin Houghton: each layer outputs a fixed number of feature maps which they call the growth rate, so that, you know, you can't really that way, like.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, in in dense net, or like in resnet, like, you might have 64 channels in and 64 channels out, and and one layer and one convolution layer, not a whole block, but just one layer where you're not doubling the amount of channels. But you just go from 64, and you map. Guess what? From 64 well, can't really do that with dense net. Because, like, let's say, the input is, I don't know 16 channels.
Benjamin Houghton: And you map to 16 channels. Well, every single time you do that, you guess what you're gonna have 16 more channels and every single layer. And it's gonna add up really fast. So what's common to see is when we'll see the full architecture here in a minute. But what normally you'll see is like, you'll go 16 to 4 right? And then the next layer is gonna be it's gonna so, then we'll and and actually, yeah. So let's say, the input is of the of the layer of the block is 16,
Benjamin Houghton: the 1st layer outputs 4. And so now the input is 20,
Benjamin Houghton: right? The input is 20 on the next layer, and it outputs 4, and then and so so on and so forth. Right? And so you're and it's gonna make a lot more sense here in a minute. So let's just look at the diagram right? But
Benjamin Houghton: let's see transition layers, right? So between the block. So here's like a dense block like, remember, the dense block is this, this is a dense block on the 1st slide. Then this is like the actual overall architecture. Right? So, we have a diagram here in a minute. But the transition layers their idea is to
Benjamin Houghton: essentially control like the
Benjamin Houghton: they reduced the number of of feature maps between the dense blocks. Because you have, like.
Benjamin Houghton: you have maybe 5 or 6 layers, and they're all producing, say, 4 or 8, or 12, or whoever many channels that they're making, each of them. And you're adding them all together. And now you have, say 6. What what you have like? 6 times 12, which is, what's that? 72. So now you have 72 channels, and so you'll run that through a transition layer, and you'll down. You'll basically reduce that maybe from 72 down to maybe back to something manageable like
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know 16 again, or whatever it is like. I'm just making up numbers, but we'll see what the actual authors of the paper, what type of numbers that they use here in a minute. And then finally, right? Like we do global average pooling. Right? Remember, I said, like, these are all gonna build off each other and like they did the same thing that resnet did with the global average pooling. And then they do the fully connected layer for for classification. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: so here is our our dense net, our our dense block diagram.
Benjamin Houghton: right?
Benjamin Houghton: And so let's take a look at this. So this is just I have 4 layers. I have. Yeah, what we call 4 layers here. So we have one dense layer, 2 dense layers, 3 and 4, and each dense layer actually has 2 convolutions, right? So we have the block input here, which is 4 channels. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: And then that's gonna go to A and look up here in the blue diagram. Right? This here's 4 channels. And that gets input into a 1 by one convolution. And the one by one convolution
Benjamin Houghton: maps to 16 in this example, it's 16. So, and actually here, the I think they call it K,
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, they call K. It's in the box they call K, the growth rate. So here the the growth weight K is 4, and they allow these, one by one convolutions to produce 4 4 k channels, and so you'll see what you'll see is the same pattern in each one of these blocks. So block one the one by one. Convolution creates 16 channels that goes into 3 by 3 convolution, and it maps to 4 channels. Okay, the output
Benjamin Houghton: is taken and concatenated here to the input and now we have 8 channels. The 8 channels go into a 1. By one convolution they map to 16 channels.
Benjamin Houghton: The 16 channels go to a 3 by 3, they map to 4 channels. So now we have 12 channels. Right? We have the original 4 input, and then we have the the 8 produced by, or the 4 produced by the blue block and or layer, and the 4 produced by the red layer. We concatenate them all together, and they go into the green layer right? So now we have 12 channels. Input
Benjamin Houghton: maps go to one by one convolution maps to 16 channels again, and then finally a 3 by 3 that maps to 4 channels, and so the same pattern just repeats itself over and over again till we're finally done with the entire layer. And guess what
Benjamin Houghton: the output is 20 channels, right? Because we have the original 4 channels. Input but and then we have 4 blocks, each producing each producing 4 channels each. So we have 20 total channels in this diagram. So this would be 1 1 block right now, this is just these numbers.
Benjamin Houghton: don't put a ton of this is the the overall pattern, but the numbers I chose here. The growth rate is is pretty typical. And they allow the one by one convolutions to produce 4 times the growth rate. But the number of input channels is kind of weird, like 4 is a small number.
Benjamin Houghton: you you know, and the output channels is is also kind of low. But I couldn't do like, you know, 12 or 16 channels, because the diagram would just you wouldn't be able to read it anymore. Alright. So let's take a look at the actual like configurations that they they might use in dense net. Right? So we have 121, 1, 69, 2 0 1 and 2, 264. So quite a few layers. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: but let's look at 1, 21, right? So again, just also very similar to resnet, we see we start off with, and you can click on this link. By the way to the paper. But I we might do that here in a minute. But we see we have the 7 by 7 convolution with the stride of 2. And it's gonna map a 220. They don't list the input size here. But the input size is 224.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's see 3 by 2, 24 by 2 24, right? And that's gonna map to this 112 by 112 image. And I don't. I guess they don't, really. It's probably in the paper. I don't know how many channels this maps to, you know.
Benjamin Houghton: I'm not sure it matters that much. Probably like 64
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. Actually, I'll show you guys that in a minute here. So I wanted to.
Benjamin Houghton: And this kind of gets a little.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's review to the rest of this chart, and then I'll we'll talk more about this. This gets kind of confusing is like keeping track of how many layers each channel has obviously. So we see that one by one convolution. And then we see the 3 by 3 convolution. And that was what we saw here right one by 1, 3 by 3, and they do it 6 times right
Benjamin Houghton: and at least in this in this block. But you can see in some of the other blocks. They do it 1224, even 16 times. And so you can imagine, like if each, if each layer you know, you're doing this 16 times, and each layer is producing, say, 12 channels, or whatever it is, or 64, or whatever the it's whatever the growth rate is K. Remember the growth rate is how many channels each layer produces right each. When I say layer, a layer is a 1 by one, followed by 3 by 3. So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. So you can look at the output sizes here. But this doesn't really tell you the whole story, because it doesn't have the channels listed, and I'm not sure why they didn't list the channels. Let's take a look
Benjamin Houghton: real quick at the paper
Benjamin Houghton: in the paper. If if you read through it, you can. It's makes a little bit more sense. But we're not gonna take. We're not. We're not gonna look too closely at this right. Now, you guys.
Benjamin Houghton: if you're curious, you can look at the paper. But yeah, they talk about the growth right here
Benjamin Houghton: 12 is the growth growth rate. That's pretty typical. I guess. But
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, and they have these bottleneck layers. Right? Which are these? Right? I guess I should have mentioned that before. So let's look at that now. So we have these bottleneck layers here
Benjamin Houghton: really do these they call the transition layers. Right? So here we can see that they're mapping to
Benjamin Houghton: The one by one. Convolutions looks like they're mapping to.
Benjamin Houghton: They're reducing the image size, and they're probably reducing the number of filters right. And we're doing pooling here. Average pool will try to. So actually.
Benjamin Houghton: the one by one convolution I'm assuming is probably reducing the number of channels I can't remember exactly, and we'll look here in a minute.
Benjamin Houghton: and the 2 by 2 is reducing the size because we see the 2 by 2 goes from 56 by 56 to
Benjamin Houghton: looks like 28 by 28, right? Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: So hopefully, that makes sense. It's not super important to get hung up on like
Benjamin Houghton: like what all these numbers are. Honestly, I probably wouldn't be going into near the amount of depth I am here in the video because we have extra time to do it. And if you're not super interested in this part of the video, you can, you can speed it up right. What's really more important to understand is like the idea of dense net, right? This interconnectivity. And that's that's what you need to take away from this. If you do are curious to know, like the like. If you know, if you are curious to know the exact implementation
Benjamin Houghton: you can do something like this.
Benjamin Houghton: Which? Where you just. And you know, we're gonna do this. When we get to the, we'll get to transfer learning in the, you know, in the next, you know, here in the future. But
Benjamin Houghton: we see that you know we can just import from torch vision this dense net model, right? So we can import.
Benjamin Houghton: We can import dense net directly from this torch vision models. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: so, yeah. So we're just inheriting from from this.
Benjamin Houghton: I'm sorry. Not here this is. This is inheriting from the Nm module class. Sorry, right down here is where we actually
Benjamin Houghton: use make use of dense net so dense. Net 1, 21
Benjamin Houghton: where we look you can. You just say weights equals true, and you get the pre-trained weights right? And then.
Benjamin Houghton: essentially like, usually, what you'll do is you'll just define your own classifier, your own last. This is just to map to the number of classes you have. Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: here we say, we see that you know number one class number of classes can be whatever you want it to be right. And then you can just you'll just adjust your final feed, forward
Benjamin Houghton: your final
Benjamin Houghton: dense layer accordingly. But what I really wanted to show you was not so much this because we're going to do a whole video on this.
Benjamin Houghton: what I wanted to show you was, if you are curious to know
Benjamin Houghton: how these models are built. So here's dense net 1, 21. And so like, let's let's take a look at this.
Benjamin Houghton: so here's the 7 by 7,
Benjamin Houghton: 2 by 2, and you can get an idea for how these models are built from this. This is just a printout right of the model, the pi torch model.
Benjamin Houghton: So we have the 7 by 7, with the 2 by 2 stride, which again we saw this in in resnet. It maps from it maps of 2, 2, 4, image, 2, 2, 4 by 2, 2, 4 to a 1, 12 by 1 12 image. And then after that, let's see, yeah, just some basic stuff like again, like it should be implied at this point that
Benjamin Houghton: you're gonna be pretty much do unless I say otherwise. Or for some like, you're unless you have a really good reason. Typically, you're gonna be doing batch normalization. And Ray Lou, after every single convolution. Layer. Okay? Not necessarily pooling. But for sure.
Benjamin Houghton: you're going to want to be doing activations. And it's pretty much universally at this point where we use Raylu in these models, at least, these, these convolutional neural networks and batch normalization unless you have some other
Benjamin Houghton: good reason to do so. This is what you're gonna be doing alright. So let's see.
Benjamin Houghton: we see here, this is the input channels is 3 and it maps to 64 channels. So now we know we have 64 channels. Okay, cool. And then let's look at the 1st dense layer the first.st So here's the 1st dense block, and then here's the 1st layer on the 1st block we have 64 channels, and
Benjamin Houghton: we're going to. Oh, this is a batch, normalization, Raylu, and then convolution. So here's the 1st convolution. We have our one by one convolution. Here we go from 64 to 1, 28. So that tells me right there with the growth rate is so, the growth rate of this network is going to be 32, then, because, remember, K is equal to in the first, st the one by one, convolutions are allowed to output 4 K channels
Benjamin Houghton: where K is the growth rate. And so here K equals 32. And so if I look at the convolution 3 by 3, I see I have 32 output channels. Okay? So just like what we thought right? Well, let's look at the next layer now. So now dense layer layer 2 of the 1st block.
Benjamin Houghton: It's going to take the input from the 1st layer, and it's going to take the original input into the block. So the input channels should be, guess what they should be 32. Because this outputted 32, and the input channels was 64. So we see 96 channels
Benjamin Houghton: come into this layer. So convolution 96, the 128, because the one by one always maps to 4 k. And the 3 by 3 always maps to K channels. At least that's the pattern in in the way, you know, for dense net. But again, like the numbers aren't probably as like we know that these numbers work pretty well. That's the author's research, and wrote. But we know that.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, it's really more about the idea of dense net and the interconnectivity of the convolutional neural networks.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? Or con interconnectivity of the convolutional layers. Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: layer 2. Let's look at layer 3. So now the input is 128, because this layer outputs 32 channels and it gets concatenated with the other 96. Okay, which came from the original input in layer one and so on and so forth. So each time we just add 32 layers. Okay, all the way down to layer 6, we see, layer 6 gets in 224. And so this is what I mean, like we have to. We. They need these transition layers to kind of
Benjamin Houghton: this number, because this is a really big number. And so at the end of this layer we have 224 plus 32
Benjamin Houghton: channels. And so the transition layer gets an input of 256 channels. And so now we need to reduce that number to keep the network kind of manageable in size, and we go from. Let's see, 256, and we map it down.
Benjamin Houghton: We have a normalization, a relu right? And then finally, a 1 by one convolution. And all it does is it maps from basically it reduces the size of the input, it cuts it in half because it maps it from 2, 5, 6 to 1, 2, 8.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay. And then the average pooling is gonna cut. This cuts the channels in half, and then this cuts the image size in half.
Benjamin Houghton: and and then we start all over again. Right? So we have a hundred 28 channels now. So it's
Benjamin Houghton: it's more channels than this layer, which was 64. So it's twice the number of channels, 1, 28. But
Benjamin Houghton: in block 2. That's it's half the it's a
Benjamin Houghton: it's half the image size, right? So you know, the image size into this layer here
Benjamin Houghton: should have been, if we do a, and actually, this is probably where we can go back here like we see that it was a 56. But you see that the
Benjamin Houghton: the input image size in the block 2 is 28 by 28. So this might be way more. This is probably way, more information and more detail than you guys really ever need to know. I wouldn't expect you to memorize this. I would just kind of expect you to have like an understanding of how this, how this works and understanding of the overall general pattern of the of the model. But you wouldn't be expecting, necessarily memorize these numbers, but should be kind of a waste of time, in my opinion, especially when you can do something like this
Benjamin Houghton: and print it out for yourself, especially now that you know how to read this diagram right? And and you understand the architecture. Alright. So that's dense net. Let's see the last model we're gonna talk about today is mobile net, which is kind of a neat one it's a little bit different than the other than the other 3 mobile net is an efficient Cnn for mobile computer vision applications cool. So it's optimized for
Benjamin Houghton: low latency, reduced memory usage and smaller model size. So I know, like in the paper they they wrote they were like, Oh, it's for Mobile, and you know, cell phones or whatever. But you know, I think this model is useful anywhere where you have reduced computational power, or you want to be as efficient as possible, you know. Sometimes it doesn't take
Benjamin Houghton: a sledgehammer to nail nail in, you know you can do something smaller, something more manageable, like a like a hammer. Right? You don't always need the most biggest powerful tool there is. All right. So
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, again, like we're, it's again, like.
Benjamin Houghton: I know, like this is for object, detection, classification, face recognition. So all these different things right? I know right now, we're really mo mainly focused on classification. But that is gonna that is gonna change right like this is this is just where we start right like, because these modern architectures that's how they were all compared to each other, right? But like you can use residual con connections in a segmentation model. So I know we we we haven't talked about
Benjamin Houghton: advanced segmentation models yet, but we will. And you know, segmentation models is a different type of task than the classification task where we're we're segmenting images.
Benjamin Houghton: but we can absolutely use these techniques like dense net and
Benjamin Houghton: residual connections and densely connected layers in these other types of models. Okay? So anyways, yeah, so this this also inspired the efficient net. Right? What the advantages we already talked about right? So sufficient for the mobile, for Mobile and I/O and Internet of thing devices.
Benjamin Houghton: Low computational costs. Trade off obviously, is lower accuracy, and it requires tuning for latency versus performance balance. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: So let's talk about the mobile net architecture. And while it's while the mobile net architecture is
Benjamin Houghton: simpler in a sense, it's going to take us more time than Resnet and Densenet, because it's kind of a new idea. This is something you probably haven't really been exposed to, even if you are familiar with convolutional neural networks. And this is the idea of these depth, wise, separable convolutions. Right? So
Benjamin Houghton: standard convolutions are computationally expensive. Right? We we each every single out. And what does that mean? Like every single output channel. So here's an output channel, right? It's and it's made up of. So
Benjamin Houghton: hold on. Let me go back to my pencil here. And let's say we have all these inputs. We have this blue channel. We have this green channel. We have this orange channel right? And every. And and let's well, this is just one single channel that we're gonna worry about on the output, right? We have one single output channel.
Benjamin Houghton: and this channel has to filter every single one with a convolution operation. Every single one of these inputs to produce its channel right? So the kernel slot. It has a kernel for all 3. It has a. It has a kernel for this red output channel has its own kernel for the blue channel.
Benjamin Houghton: for the green channel and for the orange channel, and it doesn't share these kernels with the other channels. The other output channels. So here's another. Here's another output channel. Right? Here's a here's the the pink output channel. That's probably a bad color, because it looks like the red, but the pink channel
Benjamin Houghton: it there is like no, the red channel is not going to share any of its filters or any of its weight, param any of its weights with the with the with the red channel. So the Red Channel convolves all 3 of these, and adds them all together, you know or does, it would do. In this case it would be like a say it was a 3 by 3 kernel, so it'd be 3 by 3 by 3, because you have 3
Benjamin Houghton: your, the size of your kernel is 3 by 3, and then your depth is 3, because there's 3 input channels, and that one filter
Benjamin Houghton: would create this red channel, and then the pink channel would have its own filter. And so you're doing a full convolution of an image for every single output channel. You have to convolve every single input channel. And so that's what they mean by it's it's computationally expensive. And we're gonna I introduce this idea of depth, wise, separable convolutions.
Benjamin Houghton: here. And it's gonna that's gonna help
Benjamin Houghton: reduce some of this complexity, right? So if you look here, in the depth the depth, wise convolutional uses something called the concept of groups, which is actually is, which is actually in the pie torch documentation so you could
Benjamin Houghton: write your own. I mean, you could do any of these models from scratch if you wanted to. But so here we have this idea of groups, right? And and so we're gonna look at a diagram in a minute. But just I just wanted you to be aware there is this groups keyword argument, and the default value is one. So that's a normal convolution. When you have one group right? If you and we'll see it here in a minute what number of groups means? Okay, so we have the depth, wise convolution which is called spatial filtering.
Benjamin Houghton: And then we have point-wise convolutions, which is really a fancy way of saying one by 1, 1 by one convolution. So the one by one convolution, when when we talk about depth, wise, separable convolutions. We like to call the point wise convolutions one by ones, all right. And so this is a pretty big reduction in computation, right? So mobile net reduces computation
Benjamin Houghton: on a case by case basis by about, you know, 8 or 9 times right? So for 3 by 3 convolution. And so here's the ratio, and if you look at the paper you can look at this where they come up with these numbers in more detail. They go through. How you determine this. This cost right, this comp this complexity of the layer. But this is the ratio. So, for if you were to do a death wise versus a normal convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: You're gonna it's gonna be equal to one over N, which is the number of output channels which is usually a pretty small number. So this doesn't really
Benjamin Houghton: contribute a large amount top plus
Benjamin Houghton: the kernel size. So as we see that, like as the kernel, if the kernel size, which again again, 3 by 3, go, all going all the way back to Vgg. Right? This is why Vgg is important, right? It started this 3 by 3 resnet built upon it, dense net built upon it. And now we have mobile net also, using the 3 by 3, which is the most common by far nowadays. We have these 3 by 3 convolutions.
Benjamin Houghton: so that's the kernel size here, which is one over. This is this turns out to be one over 9, plus, you know, whatever one over 32 is, which is a smallish number.
Benjamin Houghton: So you can see the ratio is about is about it's between, you know, it's it's let. It's
Benjamin Houghton: It's not quite one over 9. It's but it's not, you know. It's not quite one over 8. But usually between these 2 numbers, right between one over between 9 or 8 times reduced in computational complexity. Again, this is the ratio right? So it takes this, the where the bottom would represent
Benjamin Houghton: a normal convolution operation. It's going to take 9 times as many computations, roughly or roughly, 8 times as many computations as a depth wise, separable convolution would. And so this is going to come into play here on the next couple of slides. But let's kind of talk about like, what is a what is
Benjamin Houghton: What is a a group wise or I'm sorry, a depth, wise, separable convolution. So in order to talk about that, we 1st need to understand what what a group is. And a group is quite simply the a single group just means it's it's the number of input groups. Right? So we have an input, that input is in this example is 7 by 7. But I've padded it here. So now it's 9 by 9, right? So we have 8 channels. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: And we have an image that is now 9 by 9, because it's been padded. It was originally 7 by 7. Okay. So
Benjamin Houghton: the
Benjamin Houghton: fill in order to if I was gonna filter this right? And I wanted to have with a 3 by 3 kernel, which is pretty typical, and I wanted to have 8 put 8 output channels. Then I need 8 filters. And so what do my filters look like? Well, they look like 8. I have 8 filters.
Benjamin Houghton: I have 8 input channel and I, I have 8 input channels. And then I have a 3 by 3 kernels. So that's the size of my filters. And here are my filters right down here. And each one of these filters is gonna slide across this input right slide across this input and convolve it right and do the the convolution operation.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, again. Like I said, each
Benjamin Houghton: this filter here, you know, this light pink one produces this light pink channel, this darker one produces the next channel, so on and so forth. Like I said, each output channel has its own.
Benjamin Houghton: has its own filter that it uses to filter the input channels all right. And so this should be nothing new to you. And we can actually calculate the complexity. So this is directly from the mobile net paper we and this is pretty close. This isn't exactly close, because actually, this doesn't take into account the bias. So there is like one more. It's pretty. It's insignificant computationally like this is the
Benjamin Houghton: by far the majority. But just just be aware, like this isn't the exact number, but it's it's it's close enough like, because it's gonna be orders. The the bias is like orders of magnitude. It's insignificant right when we talk about the overall convolution operation. So, assuming no bias, this is approximately what the complexity would be.
Benjamin Houghton: for this operation. Right? So well, when we do a convolution, we have the kernel size right? 3 by 3. Okay, that makes sense. So we have 9 values. And it's gonna do what it's gonna do
Benjamin Houghton: it's basically gonna slide across your input which is 7 by 7. And if it's padded, you're gonna do 4, you're gonna do 49 convolutions. Essentially right? So when this kernel slides across. You know, if we had an input like this, you know, kernel the kernels here and then it. It moves one spot to the right, and then it does convolution. Then it was one spot to. This is a terrible drawing. I apologize. Let's see if I can do that a little bit better. Right? So if say, this is a 4 you know, it's padded
Benjamin Houghton: right? And
Benjamin Houghton: so it's 9 by 9, but the kernel is 3 by 3, so it sits right here. And so the center value goes in and goes in index 1 1. This is where it starts, so it it does the 1st convo. It goes one here, and then it moves one spot to the right. It does another convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: right? So let me let me try. Let me see if I can draw this a little bit better with
Benjamin Houghton: different colors. Maybe that maybe that'll help.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay. So here's my input, I'm gonna make the input, we'll make the input blue
Benjamin Houghton: just to make this a little bit better. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: And we assume it. You know, we know it's padded. So so here's the padding.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: And then the 1st operation is is this, 3 by 3
Benjamin Houghton: kernel right here, and the value is going to go right here in this one by right, you know, right here in this one by one cell. Okay? And then
Benjamin Houghton: we slide the kernel over one spot. So now the kernel is here, right here.
Benjamin Houghton: and so now. The kernel is you know. Only one spot shifted to the right one pixel to the right, and its value goes in right there, right right in the center of that blue
Benjamin Houghton: right? And then we shifted over one time. Right? So now it's here in the green.
Benjamin Houghton: and so on, and so forth, right and then
Benjamin Houghton: orange right? I know this isn't probably the best drawing. It's kind of hard to draw a convolution kernel sliding across an input image. But hopefully, you understand that right?
Benjamin Houghton: you should from the convolution lectures. But
Benjamin Houghton: if you know, if the input is
Benjamin Houghton: the input here is 7 by 7 with the padding that kernel can slide across 7 times so it can slide across. It can move 7 places in this direction. And then it's going to move 7 places in this direction. So it's why we get to 7 by 7 here. And it's a 3 by 3 kernel, because each each convolution is going to be.
Benjamin Houghton: It's gonna be 9 operations, right? It's gonna be
Benjamin Houghton: You know the kernels 3 by 3. So there's 3 values or 9 values being multiplied by the 9 values in the image. And guess what we're going to do that for all 8 channels. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: be in you know, each kernel is has each kernel has its own channel. It's responsible for. And so it's gonna do. It's gonna convolve the entire input channel, the entire image. And then, yeah, it's it's done right. But it's yours. Also, you know, you're you're gonna have
Benjamin Houghton: right? You're gonna have
Benjamin Houghton: So each kernel is going to do 3 by 3
Benjamin Houghton: by 7, by 7 operations for its for its channel right? And then each filter has 8 kernels.
Benjamin Houghton: and there's 8 filters total. So that's where the 8 by 8 comes in right? So pause. The video that doesn't make sense to you. You know. Or if you don't really fully understand it, you can ask me
Benjamin Houghton: question about it, all right? So that's where that number come. That's where this comes on. This complexity comes from.
Benjamin Houghton: And so like, we have this relatively modestly sized network. Okay? Or I guess convolution operation where we only have. I mean, this is pretty small, right? Only 8 channels. 9. But like we're used to seeing more channels, we're used to seeing bigger images, I mean 9 by 9, eventually further in the network, or 7 by 7. They kind of start getting to be smaller in size, but 8. Normally, there's many more channels. So this is a relatively small operation. You see, the complexity is is quite large. 28,000.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? And so this is with a single group convolution.
Benjamin Houghton: So what is a? So what's now? And and let's look at the idea on the next slide here of 2 groups. So here is a 2 group convolution. And so now
Benjamin Houghton: we have. What we've done is taken the same input right? The same input, here, 8 by 9. By 9 we've split it into 2. We split it in half. Essentially, we've broken into 4 by 4, like we took the channel. We took half the channels and split them over here and put other half the channels over here. So now we have 2 inputs instead of one, and they're half the size. And and now.
Benjamin Houghton: like we, we still have 8 output channels right? Our output is still 8 by 7 by 7, as we saw here, 8 by 7 by 7.
Benjamin Houghton: But now we have.
Benjamin Houghton: Now we have. The filters are actually half the size. We see the 8 by 4, by 3, by 3, because each of these filters only has 4 channels. Input, okay, so we, we've essentially cut the size of the channels. We cut the number of channel in half. And so
Benjamin Houghton: these Chan, these filters, these red filters, I should have used a red color here, maybe. But these red filters are gonna convolve. This input group one, and these blue filters are gonna convolve this input group 2. And so they're not gonna like these blue filters aren't gonna go over here. And these red filters okay? And and no, they're not gonna do that. They're not gonna go over there. Okay, they're just gonna do their respective. Input, so essentially, you've
Benjamin Houghton: you know, you've reduced the
Benjamin Houghton: you've cut the yeah again, you cut the input in half and you cut the filter sizes in half so we can do our same computational efficiency calculation here, right? And we see, okay, now, it's 14,000, right? So we use the same formula here. But now the input channels is 4, and the output channels is 4 for each one of these separate operations. So and you know.
Benjamin Houghton: and then, but we do it twice. Right? So it's you know, we you know, it happens 2 times. So I multiply by 2 here.
Benjamin Houghton: and that gets us 14,000, and we see that we've essentially what we've done. We've we've cut it directly in half is what we've done. So now we have the group size 2 groups. Now, each filter doesn't get to see. So that's a disadvantage here, right? These blue filters. They don't see what's over here on the right.
Benjamin Houghton: They don't, these blue filters, they don't know what's, you know. They don't know what's what these, what these features look like, and the red ones the red ones they're like, well, we don't know what these ones look like. Right? So they they miss out on some of the features. That's that's the trade off here. Okay.
Benjamin Houghton: but this is the idea of groups. And we can now go to a depth. Wise convolution. So depth, wise convolution just means that the number of groups is equal to the number of input channels. Okay, so if M here, yeah, M, we say, is the input channels, M is equal to 8.
Benjamin Houghton: So that means we need to have 8 groups. Okay, that means groups is equal to 8. Okay, if you did that, if you did, groups equals 8 in pi torch, you would do a depth wise convolution. Now this isn't a full depth, wise, separable convolution. This is just the depth, wise convolution part. And so it's the same idea here now, where we've taken the input. And now, instead of splitting into 2 groups, we have 8. We have 8 separate groups. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: We have one.
Benjamin Houghton: 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, right? And so let's pretend like this magenta filter. It filters the 1st one. Right? This blue filter filters, the second want channel. This I don't know. Jungle green filter filters, the 3rd channel, so on and so forth, right and and we noticed that there's only one each, each one of these filters, each one of these. Then they are filters of a single kernel.
Benjamin Houghton: you know. Each filter only has one kernel, and so the kernel, each kernel, and remember one channel, one channel, one kernel, one kernel, one channel, right? So each kernel filters a single channel and any well, each filter singles, each filter of a single kernel has a single channel input and a single channel output. And so here we've we've we have a
Benjamin Houghton: you know. You can already probably tell. This is going to greatly reduce the computational cost. But the downside again is like this magenta.
Benjamin Houghton: Let's see, let's see if we have magenta here. This magenta filter doesn't know what's here. It doesn't know what's here. It's it's wondering hey? Like. What are all? What's what are all these channels about? And we're gonna address that here in a minute. But this is the downside right? It doesn't. It doesn't get to see any of these features. However, we've vastly reduced our complexity right? And so actually, if you take that original number, which was 28, 2, 2, 4, and you divide that number by 8.
Benjamin Houghton: Guess what you will get this. You will get 3, 5.
Benjamin Houghton: I'm I'm trying to like. Do the math. Is that exactly right?
Benjamin Houghton: should be like close. Let me let me see if I plug these numbers in correctly should be.
Benjamin Houghton: Pull my calculator here.
Benjamin Houghton: Make sure I plug these numbers in right? Let's see, we have. Oh, or one slide too far.
Benjamin Houghton: Can't see that yet. It's top secret.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, where's my calculator.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright. So let's see input channels. Yeah, 3 by 3, by one by one by 7 by 7.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, that looks correct. Let me see if I punch this in right? 3 times 3 oops. Yeah, times
Benjamin Houghton: 7 times 7. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: Right? And then we multiply.
Benjamin Houghton: What did I? Oh, I typed this in wrong.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay? Well, it's 9 by 9, by 49, right?
Benjamin Houghton: By that, by 8, yeah, 35, 28. Okay? Let's see if we multiply this by 8. Yeah, exactly. That's what I thought right? So I was making sure I was doing some quick
Benjamin Houghton: mental math, that it was approximately the same number.
Benjamin Houghton: 28, 2, 2, 4, right? So yeah, we multi, we divide. So we have 8 groups. Right? So initially, we had the complexity of 28,000 with a single group. And we have turned that into 8 groups when we reduce our complexity by a factor of 8. Right? We see here, okay, cool. That's a huge difference. Right?
Benjamin Houghton: and so
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, I mean that that's a huge difference. Again, like we talked about the disadvantage. The disadvantage is that each filter only gets to see one input channel. And so it's not gonna build as quite as complex relationships. However, there is one thing we can do to get around that right at least a little bit. And that's this idea of the point. Wise
Benjamin Houghton: the point. Wise
Benjamin Houghton: convolution. Okay? And so what is a point? Wise convolution? I already said it before, but it's a 1 by one.
Benjamin Houghton: It's a 1 by one convolution. So in this diagram we have this exact right about here is where. So right here I'll draw a line. This is where the point wise convolution starts and the depth wise ends right. So we the top, left this part of the diagram up here. This is the depth, wise portion right and the bottom down here. This where the we have the red filters and the red output. This is the point wise. And so what's going on here? Well.
Benjamin Houghton: actually, we produce this
Benjamin Houghton: this output channel that you know from the depth wise. Here we have 8, this 8 by 7 by 7 output. Here, then, you know, each of these channels was only only got information from a single channel. So to remedy that we take these one by one, convolutions that reach across the entire input so now here groups.
Benjamin Houghton: groups will say groups were 8 up here in this portion. But now in this portion groups is going to be equal to one again. And so now we have
Benjamin Houghton: each filter, albeit each filter is is only one by only, as one by one kernels they get information across all 8 channels, and so this each of these little filters?
Benjamin Houghton: they they reach across again, like all yeah, all you would when you filter this. This, let's look at this. Oh.
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, we we can.
Benjamin Houghton: Sorry I'm I'm messing around with my ipad here.
Benjamin Houghton: mess! It was like zooming in and out on me, but you couldn't see it on the on the recording. So anyways,
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, we see that these kernels or these filters have 8 have 8 little
Benjamin Houghton: weights in them, and they're gonna go all the way across the input channels. Okay? And there's no need for padding here, because the one by one can is gonna slide across and get hit all 49 pixels.
Benjamin Houghton: And will you let this output of 8 by 7 by 7?
Benjamin Houghton: And so that's the point wise. And so now. From the paper you can get the point. Wise complexity. So here's the depth. Wise complexity. 35, 28 and then we have the point. Wise complexity
Benjamin Houghton: 31, 36. And then finally, we have the total complexity you can add up. It's 6, 6 6,664. And so it's roughly, you know, it's a lot, I guess, in this example, with 8 channels in this small little toy example it's a pretty significant difference, because, remember, it was 28 K. Roughly. Now, the complexity is like, roughly, a little bit over a little bit over 6 k. Right? So pretty big difference,
Benjamin Houghton: and computational efficiency. I guess the one thing. I guess I'll go back to this slide. I just want to point out one thing if you guys are interested. And how I know I talked about the complexity of a normal convolution layer, the depth, the complex, the complexity of the depth. Wise is pretty simple. Because here the only difference is the number of
Benjamin Houghton: the complexity of the number of input. So this number and number of input channels and
Benjamin Houghton: number of output channels is the is equal to, they're both equal to one. So if you use the original, so on the left, I have the original formula, right of a normal layer, and I say one times one, but I do it 8 times, whereas in the book they just say, well, it doesn't really matter it it just the number of input channels number output channels equal to each other. M equals N or
Benjamin Houghton: of the entire layer M equals n, which equals the 8.
Benjamin Houghton: And yeah, anyways, you can see like these 2 are equivalent. Right? You can convince yourself that these numbers are equivalent. And so this is the formula, they that they give you in the paper to calculate the depth, wise complexity. And then, finally, we have the and I'm not going to really go through the details. You can, if you want to read the paper you can. But the complexity of the depth, the point wise is pretty simple here. Right? It's just m times n
Benjamin Houghton: times d, because the kernel size dk, here is equal to one. So it's just one times one times input channels times output channels times the filter times the the size of the feature map, which is the input channel width and height, 7 by 7
Benjamin Houghton: which gives. And so, yeah, you can calculate. This file number. And again, like this is in the paper. And there's links to this presentation in the paper here, and also
Benjamin Houghton: on the next slide right here. So now that we know what the
Benjamin Houghton: So here's the configurations of the of the of the mo of of mobile net.
Benjamin Houghton: yeah, you can. You can click on this. And you can. You can read more about it. But
Benjamin Houghton: let's see, what are the big takeaways for this diagram? Here? Well, we have a 3. Let's see
Benjamin Houghton: the filter. Okay, this is I I kinda I'm gonna applaud. Well, they didn't they? Still don't. They still don't have it. They still have it backwards. I'm not gonna applaud them. Sorry! I don't like when they list
Benjamin Houghton: the Channel dimension last. This is really annoying. Here. So this, this is the Channel dimension. So what is this?
Benjamin Houghton: Maybe I maybe I'm maybe it's a lost cause. Me trying to teach you guys this way. But I really don't like this notation where the channels listed last. So the filter. What does this mean here? So they have certain 3 by 3, by 3, by 32. So that what they're saying is, they have 32 filters.
Benjamin Houghton: They have 3 input channels. The kernel size height is 3, and the kernel size width is 3. So that's the way pi torch would, you know is gonna package your data?
Benjamin Houghton: right? So you know, maybe the 32 and the 3 can be slopped like the number of filters and the number of channels, but I think it makes more sense to have the I think you would. You would see it like this. In pi torch. I'm not sure I've ever really dug into the exact dimensions of the filters, but I know that the actual image data, the channel is always listed first, st right? Or actually, that's not entirely true. You can have the channel listed last.
Benjamin Houghton: But you have to tell Pi Torch that. And then pi torch is going to be like, okay. Well, since you're making me do it this way, I'll just fix it for you before I do the convolution operation. And that's literally what happens, you have to tell it that. So it knows to put the, you know, basically permutate the the dimensions before it does the operation.
Benjamin Houghton: alright. So yeah, let's okay. So that's the filter shape here. Now that we know how to read this, we see the input size again, we see that same input. Size, 224 by 224 RGB, images, we have a filter. We're gonna have, we have. So input we're gonna input 3 filters output. I'm sorry. Input 3 channels. Output 32 channels with a 3 by 3 kernel
Benjamin Houghton: and so then we go to the next layer, and then we have the one by one. So this is the, this is the depth wise, separable.
Benjamin Houghton: actually, let's see. Yeah. 3 by 3.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay, so
Benjamin Houghton: I'm just looking at this. I just realized that this 1st layer is actually not. It's just like a normal combo. It appears to me that this is just either. I'd have to read the paper. It doesn't. It's not super
Benjamin Houghton: pertinent, but it looks like this. First, st this 1st one is just a normal convolution, right. It's a 3 by 3, by 3, by 32. It's not. It's not depth wise, and it's not point wise. And then the next. This layer right? And then the very next layer is depth wise, right? So
Benjamin Houghton: we have 32 input channels. Which means we're gonna have 32 output channels. And and it's gonna be 3 by 3. So you have 32 filters.
Benjamin Houghton: and they're each, have they each have a single 3 by 3 kernel. So there's no, there's no longer that 4th dimension here, right? Because each filter is just a single kernel. So this is the depth wise, and then the next one's the point wise. So we have the one by one kernel, 32 input channels and 64 output channels.
Benjamin Houghton: Yeah, has to be 64, because the input is here is 32. And so, yeah, so now we see, yeah, 64. And then, now, the input size is 64, you know it'd be nice is that you know, these authors. They all like talk about building off the image. They all talk about building off like the previous architectures, and they use like.
Benjamin Houghton: Oh, we, you know we are inspired by Bgg or whatever, but then, like they can't, they don't standardize their their notation. So you have to like. Figure out like they're they're like high. It's like hieroglyphics here, almost sometimes what they're what they're trying to say. But that's the pattern
Benjamin Houghton: where we see the one by one is the point. Wise convolutions, and we see the 3 by 3 is the depth wise convolutions. And I guess that's what Dw stands for in this chart.
Benjamin Houghton: right? And so you can see looks like the 1st number. That's the input features. And the second number. That's the output features, right? Because if we see the input here it was 32, and then the output. Here we see on the input for the next layers is 64 channels, right? So this second number is the number of output channels they desire. So we go 64, 1, 28, 2, 56, 5, 12, and then finally looks like we do.
Benjamin Houghton: We get down to a 7 by 7 image. And we do that average pooling just like Resnet did. And then we feed that into a fully connected classifier. And then finally, Softmax, okay? And so. And this this architecture is, it does pretty good. I mean it it vastly. It vastly reduces the number of I guess I don't have, you know, and I don't have it linked here. I apologize. But you can search. I have
Benjamin Houghton: mobile net linked here.
Benjamin Houghton: So maybe we look at this somewhere in here.
Benjamin Houghton: I know they talk about like the computational efficiency compared to like resnet and stuff like that. And
Benjamin Houghton: how many fewer parameters they have like they have a lot less parameters, and they almost do. I mean they don't do as good. But well, here you go like, here's here's Bgg 16 and we know that
Benjamin Houghton: we know Vgg has like way too many parameters. That's partly because of the fully connected layer.
Benjamin Houghton: Anyways, I it's not super important. But somewhere in here. Yeah, they should compare
Benjamin Houghton: the number of parameters, I mean. Let's look at this. This is this might be interesting to look at, so
Benjamin Houghton: mobile net has 6.8 million parameters. And you know.
Benjamin Houghton: you know, this is like a object detection, though this isn't. Yeah, look, that's
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. So like, it's like I was saying before,
Benjamin Houghton: they do, they can do a bunch of different tasks with this, which is written directly into the paper, which is kind of cool. Let's I was, you know, we try to compare apples to apples we haven't really talked about. We will get to object detection and stuff. But not today.
Benjamin Houghton: Right now, we're just concerned with the classification I'm looking for like an image net comparison.
Benjamin Houghton: But I'm not seeing it. I don't want to waste
Benjamin Houghton: you guys time watching me scroll through. Oh, here we go. Imagenet.
Benjamin Houghton: Okay. Image net accuracy. Alright, so mobile. Net 70%. Vgg 71 point. We know that Vgg isn't isn't like the latest and greatest, but it's a good baseline and we have far, far fewer parameters, you know.
Benjamin Houghton: This is a little misleading, in my opinion.
Benjamin Houghton: It'd be kind of nice to see this.
Benjamin Houghton: Here's Alexnet, which is another popular model like it has 60 million, I mean, you can see like
Benjamin Houghton: it's I mean, the idea is mobile. That's right up there. I'd like to see this like compared against resonant. I don't.
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know. But anyways, the idea is way. Fewer parameters, you know, with a slight trade off, and accuracy like that's the whole idea behind behind mobile net. So it's a pretty cool architecture. And it's pretty ingenious, I think.
Benjamin Houghton: So. Alright. Alright. Finally, to wrap this up. We're gonna talk really quickly about transfer learning. And
Benjamin Houghton: we're just gonna I'm just gonna give you like the basic over overall ideas here, right? So transfer learning. Essentially, what we're gonna do is we're gonna leverage knowledge from these other models that have been pre trained. And so like, you know, Google or I don't know whoever you know, I guess pie torch has these models that have been trained on these massive data sets by whoever like Google, I don't know
Benjamin Houghton: And
Benjamin Houghton: anybody can just download the weights and and use these models. And so like. If I, you know, image net was trained on, has a thousand different classes right? It has a thousand different like car and boat and horse, and whatever else.
Benjamin Houghton: So let's say that I had some like really like I was trying to classify
Benjamin Houghton: what's a good example I don't know. Like types of.
Benjamin Houghton: I don't know. Like types of trees. Maybe I don't really know if that's a good example or not, but like something different, like where I'm not classifying just everyday objects. But I'm doing some type of classification test. Well, the thing about Vgg
Benjamin Houghton: and resnet that have been these, these architectures have been trained up on these data sets by
Benjamin Houghton: with a lot of this took a lot of time and effort to to get these models well trained, and they didn't just learn the class like the way we know that Cnn's like the 1st the 1st layer like
Benjamin Houghton: it might. It picks up on like an like. You know the way these work. Right? Let's talk about like how they work real quick. Just give a brief review which you guys probably know this, but like it doesn't just see a cat and knows it's a cat, right? It, like one filter sees the cat's ears, and, like one filter, learns to pick up on these points like like trying like these.
Benjamin Houghton: Well, I guess 2 thirds of a triangle right? I don't know. And then 1 1 filter maybe learns to pick up on like these radial lines, which are it's whiskers, and then, like one learns to like pick up on the cat's. No, that's a terrible cat nose, but who knows? Right like? So on and so forth, or or you know another one? It's cats, cat eyes right like it learns to pick up on this shape and then, but like, that's just like really basic stuff. And then
Benjamin Houghton: so maybe the 1st filter, right, it picks up on the cat's eye like the eye shape like the one. What was a cat? I look like this right? Something like that. It learns to pick up that shape. But then the next filter says, Oh, look! There's that cat shape, and there's like this round thing in it, and then the next filter is like, Oh, look! There's like this
Benjamin Houghton: cat with a eye, with a pupil shit right? And so like, it builds up these more and more complex relationships. And so the idea here and transfer learning is that these
Benjamin Houghton: these earlier layers in the network they don't really, they don't really know like they don't know what a cat is. They don't know what a dog is, or a horse or a boat. They learn to recognize shapes and patterns, and they build these like super complex relationships, and they they learn they learn like to pick up like certain traits or features, or, you know, that's why we call them feature maps right? And so we can use that feature.
Benjamin Houghton: that knowledge to do whatever we want. We can basically use resnet to extract features for us. Right? So it's kind of like thinking about like taking your data and transforming it into like a much more usable format, almost, or like extracting like really really useful information
Benjamin Houghton: cause. All that's ultimately good. It's gonna go into a feed forward network right? Like after the features have been extracted. Then we can we can put them into a feed forward network. And the feed forward network is like, Hey, based upon these features. That is a palm tree, right? Some other new task that's not part of like the image net task, or whatever like. It's not predicting a thousand classes. And that's that's how this works.
Benjamin Houghton: essentially, what you'll do is you'll load in image net, or I'm sorry not Imagenet. You'll load in resnet right? Or maybe dense net, or whatever model you want. And so let's say, this is the convolutional part, right? And maybe you and this is the this is the
Benjamin Houghton: fully connected part. So what you'll do is you'll you'll X that you'll get rid of that. Okay? And so you'll get rid of this part. Let's see, it was just erase that, and you'll have. I can change colors here, you'll define your own fully connected network. And let's say, instead of a thousand classes, let's just say I have 10. Okay, so maybe I have 2 layers here. And I define these these new layers. And then I start training my model with my data.
Benjamin Houghton: And during back propagation I'm just gonna freeze the resnet layers. So that means that these layers down here. I'm not going to back prop like, I'm not going to calculate their their gradient like. There's no need to calculate their gradient. So I'm not going to do it. And I'm not going to update their weights right? So and we're just gonna update the weights of the blue portion. Right? And so
Benjamin Houghton: you'll see this a lot. I mean, this isn't necessarily. It doesn't necessarily have to be like the resnet architecture connected to fully connected. You could do something where like this is resnet. And then maybe I have my own new convolutional neural network, right? Like, you actually see things like this where it's like, I have my new com like I have resnet. And then I have my own
Benjamin Houghton: user defined portion. And then maybe I have a fully connected part, or maybe I have resnet, followed by a completely other architecture like Unet, like, which we'll talk about when we get to segmentation. And we just use resnet to extract the features. That's the idea here. And that's essentially what transfer learning is in a nutshell. Okay?
Benjamin Houghton: yeah. So we talked about all this layer freezing. Right? We're not gonna update the basically layer freezing. This means we're not gonna update the resnet parameters. Fine tuning means we're just going to
Benjamin Houghton: right? We're just gonna fine tune, the model by maybe we should go through these in order. I'm I. I'm going backwards. Huh? So Pre. Training a model is trained on large data set like Imagenet to learn features. Right? Okay, that we talked about that. That's what Resnet did. Fine tuning the pre trained models adapted to new task right on a smaller data set. Right? So after it's trained on Resident, say for a year, not a year. Let's say, let's say a long time like
Benjamin Houghton: 100 HI don't know. We wanted to classify species of of plants now, which is probably like a really big thing on the app store, right? I'd say people pay money for that, right? Or like diagnosing plant diseases or whatever thing you want. That's a that's a kind of a cool classification or fast right? How many of you are always like what is wrong with my house plant right? And like, I'm always like trying to take pictures of it. And then, like, you know, it'd be really nice if somebody trained a really good model to like diagnose my house plants for me.
Benjamin Houghton: That would be an awesome project, right? And then finally, layer freezing right? So you know, often we don't like it's gonna take a lot of time and effort, and it's, you know, we might not want to unlearn what resonance already learned. So if Resnet learned a bunch of like really good things, really good habits, then we might not want to update the weights, or it or it might be computationally expensive to do it. So we might freeze its layers. Okay? So we talked about all those things.
Benjamin Houghton: okay, so different approaches inductive. So the source and the the source and target tasks are different, but the model is adapted to it to the target task.
Benjamin Houghton: right? So that's kind of you know, this could be like this could be. The idea here is so this could be. Think of this as
Benjamin Houghton: I have better examples, but we haven't talked about segmentation yet, so you might like resnet might have been trained on a classification task. But you want to say segment, Coke bottles from a picture, or pictures of
Benjamin Houghton: mountain dew cans. I don't know something, or cell phones or faces from an image. Right? That's a segmentation task. So that's an example where resnet might be adapted, where you add on new layers, or whatever. So that's inductive. Or maybe you're going from classification to I don't know regression where you have a picture or a person resonant was trained again on classification. But maybe you're going to do regression, and you're going to predict the age of a person. And you know that's a that would be a new
Benjamin Houghton: task
Benjamin Houghton: where you're you're kind of adapting to a new task, transductive. So a new same task, but different domains again. So that's that's that. One's pretty simple like that was like my house plant example, where we use resnet to to classify different houseplant diseases. I don't know something like that. Domain adaptation focuses on model train in one domain to work well on a different but related domain. So
Benjamin Houghton: that's you know, domain is, that's kind of
Benjamin Houghton: It's very similar to.
Benjamin Houghton: It's kind of open, ended in the sense like it could be a combination, I think, of inductive or transductive, but you know alright, so feature, extraction.
Benjamin Houghton: and fine tuning right? So we talked about about both these approaches already.
Benjamin Houghton: All right. And again, like you don't have to do like these aren't necessarily. These aren't necessarily mutually exclusive, or they could be, you know, you could do one or the other. You could do both. It doesn't matter. You could do fine tuning where you unfreeze some of the layers. You could just do feature, extraction, and freeze all the layers that you know. It's kind of up to you. And we'll see it's pretty easy to to determine which layers you want to freeze, and which ones you don't want to freeze, and pie towards
Benjamin Houghton: literally just like a single like for loop.
Benjamin Houghton: Alright!
Benjamin Houghton: alright. So some of the applications of transfer learning. Obviously, computer vision like, that's what this class is obviously all about. Right. But I mean, there's other ones, too. Nlp,
Benjamin Houghton: speech recognition. And and you know, I think the advantages are probably pretty clear at this point. Right faster convergence, and starting from scratch leverages, learned representations of large data sets where a lot of really smart people spend a lot of time and effort to train
Benjamin Houghton: these these really complex models, and then often leads to better performance with limited data. Yep, okay, cool. And that's it. So that is the end of the video and so in the future we will talk about how to take advantage of these models and put them into use. Thanks.